# **VICTOR MANDELA**

@ vmandela99@gmail.com

+254733942277

Nairobi

in https://www.linkedin.com/in/vmand ela99

# **COMPUTER SKILLS**

R and R studio

SOL

Microsoft Word and Excel

Machine learning

Git and Github

**SPSS** 

## PERSONAL DETAILS

Github: https://github.com/vmandela99

Rpubs: https://rpubs.com/vickman

## **SUMMARY**

An data leader with more than 4 years experience as an end to end statistical solver. High - level technical analytical and machine learning expert in both quantitative and qualitative research. I strive in an environment with 80% data pipeline development and 20% skill advancement through offering practical team work trainings.

### **EDUCATION**

**University of Nairobi** 2018 - Completing in December 2020

Master of Science in Social Statistics

University of Nairobi 2012 - 2015

**Bachelor of Economics and Statistics** 

Mecheo High School 2008 - 2011

**KCSE** 

Mathematics A

Data Camp Online Campus 2020

Data Science using R

Distinction

## **EXPERIENCE**

#### **Data Scientist**

October 2020 - To date

Xetova

- Lead the data department
- Regularly train and build capacity of interns and the data science team on best practices of big data and machine learning techniques.
- Designing workflows for data engineering, model building and deployment procedures.
- Advise on the product and data model development process
- Lead in building and implementing product and data models
- Conduct quality assurance on existing product and data models produced by peers.
- Provide holistic support in the formulation, creation, implementation and testing of machine learning and artificial intelligence frameworks for the company.

Msc Fellowship

- Conduct research on efficacy of paediatric treatment guidelines for severe pneumonia in Kenya.
- Application of Statistical and Machine learning techniques.
- Application of kNN, bootstrap aggregating, logistic regression, and random forests models.
- prediction and focasting using machine learning algorithm.
- Conduct high level on descriptive statistics, hypothesis testing, diagnostic analysis ,and predictive modelling using suitable machine learning techniques.
- Employing statistical tools to interpret data sets, locating trends and patterns that may assist to inform crucial insights.

### Population council

Sep 2019 - Dec 2019

Graduate Research assistant

- · Assists with academic research.
- Assists with the editing and preparation of manuscripts.
- Performs research work in archives, through interviews, online, or whatever may be appropriate to assist the assistant's supervisor.
- Gathers and analyzes data.
- Prepares materials for submission to agencies and foundations that fund research.

**Business Analyst** 

- Using data to deliver credit scoring, customer churning and customer segmentation solution for optimization.
- Monitoring and managing customer portfolio on return on investment.
- Developing and implementing data processing quality procedures to that capture metrics and execute restrictions so as to maintain data quality for effectiveness and efficiency.
- Developing report analysis and forecast to guide business decision making.
- Liaise other departments and colleagues to establish performance standards, data quality checks, data analysis procedures and create accountable results.
- Participate in training of colleagues on best practices of data management, statistical methods and visualizations using ggplot2.
- Design surveys on Kobo-toolbox, ODK, survey monkey and Google forms for collection of data in way that promotes gain of richer insights into experience and customer behaviour.
- Perform in-depth market research and develop financial models.
- Monitoring, assessing, and anticipating risks and proactively reporting any potential risks.
- Analyzing customer behaviourial patterns, identify contributors to low performance and strategizing on remedies.
- Providing timely and informative reporting on all key performance indicators.
- Conduct in-depth research on data sources in support of project requirements.

#### **Equity Bank Limited**

June 2015 - September 2015

Intern - Risk Analytics

- Analyze and evaluate qualification of submissions to identify basic level risks.
- Provide support to project teams on the prequalification process.
- Gain understanding of risk management strategies.
- Assist with improving the overall pre-qualification analysis process and evaluating the financial rating models.

Intern, Research and Product Development

- Understanding financial management needs.
- Creating a service delivery model for financial management environment.
- Enhancing the organizational culture.

# R ACHIEVEMENTS & AWARDS -

Data Science course in R Managed to finish a data camp interactive online course.

Certified as an Ethical researcher. Successful completed the research ethics curriculum from fhi360

Certified data analyst in SPSS. This certificate is from Amref college international

Certified Credit analysis with R.



### Davis N. Bundi (PhD - "University of Nairobi"

Lecturer dbundi@uonbi.ac.ke +254710453132

### Peris Kwamboka - "Xetova Software company"

Business intelligence Analyst Kwamboka.peris@gmail.com +254722802651

#### Stanley Nyoro - "Nielsen"

Customized Intelligence Executive nyorostanley@gmail .com +254713662312



- Interpersonal skills.
- Excellent written and verbal communication skills in English.
- Excellent attention to detail.
- Proactive, service-oriented attitude.
- Strong attitude towards compliance

Jui -